Brian D. Baker

Columbus, OH, USA brian.baker.bdb@gmail.com 1-440-453-0595 www.linkedin.com/in/baker-ling github.com/baker-ling Portfolio: baker-ling.github.io/portfolio/index.html

Full-stack web developer transitioning from a career as a Japanese-English translator/interpreter Accumulated programming experience from various projects throughout education and career that is augmented by a web development bootcamp. Possesses advanced fluency in Japanese from experience living and working in Japan as well as research, analytical, presentation and project management skills honed through graduate school research & teaching duties, translation/interpretation experience, and small-scale software development projects.

POSITION SOUGHT

Full-stack software developer or ML/NLP-related developer position

SKILLS

Tech Skills: HTML, CSS, SQL, JavaScript, Visual Basic for Applications, Regex, Python (ML libraries:

Scikit-learn, TensorFlow 2), Java, Git.

 Developing PowerPoint Add-In to automate file-cleaning prior to translation using VBA, Regex, Python, and TensorFlow

• Developed online Japanese dialect data viewer with JavaScript and Google Maps

Developed online bilingual meeting note-taking app with machine translation using JavaScript and online APIs. Repository: https://github.com/baker-ling/osu bcs project1

Natural Languages: English native speaker, fluent in Japanese.

Introductory-level proficiency in Spanish, Korean, and Mandarin Chinese.

A/V: Audio equipment and online conferencing configuration

(Williams A/V Digiwave, Audio-Technica discussion system ATUC-50, Zoom with interpretation

add-on, Microsoft Teams with VoiceMeeter mixing software)

WORK EXPERIENCE

In-house Translator/Interpreter, Corporate Commercial Relations

TS Tech Americas, Inc., Reynoldsburg, OH: August 2014 – Present

- Providing simultaneous & consecutive interpretation for sales and business meetings with customers at all
 hierarchy levels, for internal technical and business reviews with executive management, for teleconferences with
 counterparts in Japan, for consultation with legal counsel on commercial issues, and for general in-office
 conversations and discussions between Japanese & English-speaking staff.
- Developed MS Office plugins in VBA to accelerate pre- and post-translation formatting.
 Received Technical Merit award at Honda's Fall 2019 CAN Conference.
- Translating between Japanese & English for sales and sales-engineering presentations to customers, for contracts and legal correspondence, and for internal reports, business plan proposals, and other correspondence.
- Developing machine-learning based system in Python to completely automate pre-translation formatting.
- Managed the adoption of computer-assisted translation technology in corporate purchasing and sales division.

Graduate Teaching Associate, Department of East Asian Languages & Literatures

The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH; September 2012 – May 2013

- Taught beginner/intermediate Japanese (in individualized and classroom settings), developed and performed lesson plans both for daily performance classes conducted in the Japanese and weekly lectures in English.
- Taught Introduction to East Asian Humanities, performing lectures on topics in China, Korea, and Japan.

Brian D. Baker

Columbus, OH, USA brian.baker.bdb@gmail.com 1-440-453-0595

www.linkedin.com/in/baker-ling github.com/baker-ling Portfolio: baker-ling.github.io/portfolio/index.html

WORK EXPERIENCE (CONTINUED)

Coordinator for International Relations (JET Program), Toyohashi City Hall, Toyohashi, Japan; July 2008 – July 2011

- Translated city government documents and correspondence between Japanese & English.
- Interpreted for delegations from foreign cities meeting with city officials and for English-speaking foreign residents using city hall services.
- Wrote and performed lessons and lectures on American culture for elementary schools and community groups.

Contract Translator, Honda R&D Americas, Inc., Raymond/East Liberty, OH; July 2007 – January 2008; employed through Next Step Resources

- Performed in-office & teleconference interpretation between Japanese & American staff relating to vehicle durability testing.
- Translated technical documents relating to vehicle durability testing for internal and external use.
- Compiled department spending for internal budget reports.

Contract Translator, American Showa, Inc., Sunbury, OH; May 2007 – July 2007; employed through Next Step Resources

- Provided interpretation between Japanese & English at shock absorber & power steering unit manufacturing plant, primarily for discussions relating to production engineering & quality.
- Translation of engineering-related technical documents and correspondence for internal use.

Web Aide, Amherst Exempted Village Schools, Amherst, OH; September 2001 – September 2002

- Designed web pages for elementary, middle, and high school teachers.
- Developed web programs for delivering dynamic content using HTML4, PHP4, & MySQL.

EDUCATION

Web Development Bootcamp, The Ohio State University, Certificate program. July 2021 – January 2022.

• Git, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, MERN stack

M.A. in Japanese Linguistics, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH. September 2011 – August 2014.

- Focus area: historical linguistics and dialectology
- Graduation project: online viewer of Japanese geographical dialect data using JavaScript and Google Maps API v3 for use in dialectology research.

10-Month Intensive Program in Advanced Japanese

Inter-University Center for Japanese Language Studies, Yokohama, Japan. September 2013 – June 2014.

B.A. in Japanese with Distinction, B.A. in International Studies (International Relations & Diplomacy Specialization) The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH. September 2002 – March 2007.

Minors: Computer and Information Science, Linguistics. Summa Cum Laude, with Honors in the Arts and Sciences

Year-long Study Abroad Program, University of Tsukuba, Tsukuba, Japan. September 2004 – July 2005.